[Uhtred] I am Uhtred,
son of Uhtred.
I was born a Saxon Lord
but raised by Danes
as a warrior.
I now serve Alfred,
the Saxon King of Wessex.
And protect this
last Kingdom of England
from Guthrum
and his Viking army.
But not all
believe in the king.
I am my father's heir.
[Uhtred] To some I am seen
as an enemy within.
With luck
he will fall in battle.
[Uhtred] It is a court without
justice where I will always
be seen a Pagan,
even through the eyes
of my pious
and now distant wife.
And so to pay off the debt on my land,
I plundered as a Viking would.
And I found a Pagan Queen.
A seer whose gift
is linked to her purity.
She is not to hump.
[Uhtred]
I am now called a traitor.
I, Brother Asser,
swear these oaths.
[Uhtred] Alfred's courts
decided I should be executed.
I request
that he dies at my sword.
You will fight to the death
[Uhtred]
Destiny is all.
[indistinct chatter]
Get out you drunk bastard!
Is he here?
With a woman who's not his wife.
Your friend is here.
May I sit? Or will I spoil the
gift of a last night of freedom?
Sit.
Do you believe
I have betrayed you, arseling?
-I don't...
-Make no mistake,
Odda had 20 men or more,
ready to swear against you.
I am here to tell you that
I am better than you right now.
I will kill you.
A warrior's death
is all I can give.
Forgive me but I am trying
to forget you are my friend.
As long as you understand.
If you have more to say,
you should say it.
Leofric! Leofric!
This isn't a fight I want.
I have been
allowed my freedom tonight
and if I could slip away,
I would.
But I cannot do that.
Reputation is all.
-I know it.
-I have feuds to settle,
promises to keep; I must live.
Then you must kill me.
-And you me.
-I intend to.
I will have the advantage.
The king's wife
is praying for me.
-God loves her.
-Someone's got to.
It's been good
to have you as my friend.
I'll make your death
quick and painless.
-Then hump my queen?
-And your wife.
But you will be
without your balls.
[soft chuckle]
I will see you tomorrow morning.
You will.
[rooster crows]
What are you thinking?
What goes on inside this head?
I was thinking how I would like
to lie with you... as a woman.
You were?
-I cannot.
-Yes, you can.
I cannot, you know I cannot,
I will lose my gift.
Who cares? The future is fate,
it won't change.
And if today I die?
I have not seen your death.
Uhtred...
The king
wishes to speak with you.
About what?
He is unsure what to wear this
morning and needs your advice.
With me.
[Alfred] Are you going to eat
all of this...
[girl] Shh...
[Alfred] ...or shall we
save half for Edward?
-[girl laughing] He's a baby.
-[door shuts]
Oh, is he? Is he really?
I had quite forgotten.
-[gasps]
-Ah, Uhtred....
-Lord... I trust you slept well.
-[woman shushing]
[Alfred] I did not.
My son is coughing
and two of my best warriors
will today try
to kill each other.
[baby coughing and crying]
Today is the feast
of Saint Cedd...
[girl] Edward...
...we have decorated
the Great Hall.
-Do you know of Saint Cedd?
-No, Lord.
Well, I like to
think of him as a symbol.
He worked in East Anglia and
Mercia and he died in Northumbria,
your part of the country.
-A man of all England.
-Exactly, Uhtred.
Which is why I am loathe to shed
Saxon blood on his day of days.
Resume, your debt, despatch
your "queen" back to Cornwalum,
and there need be no bloodshed.
Those are my terms,
and they will not change.
If Iseult returns
to Cornwalum she'll be killed.
I am prepared to resume my debt,
to save Leofric,
but Iseult must stay with me.
She is plunder and as such
she must be returned,
regardless of her fate.
I can't abandon her!
The Queen stays with me.
You are a fool.
You are a sinner,
and a heathen and I...
I have lost
my patience with you.
The fight will go ahead.
May your soul receive
its just reward.
Lord.
-[baby coos]
-Shh...
[indistinct chatter[
[Wulfhere] Make way. Make way.
Silence!
Your majesty,
Lords, ladies...
Great unwashed and stinking
people of Winchester!
[all laughing]
[Wulfhere] We are gathered
to witness justice!
We are gathered to
witness a fight to the end,
that end being death,
that end being
the fires of hell.
We are hear to witness a battle
between Uhtred, the Godless...
[crowd jeers]
...and Leofric, of Winchester!
[crowd cheers]
[Wulfhere] Take your shields.
Warriors... Are you prepared?
-I am.
-Yes.
It is to the death,
no matter how death occurs.
May God choose his victor.
Swords...
Begin!
[horse whinnies]
[crowd cheering]
[grunting]
Brother Asser, I wish you well
on your return to Cornwalum.
You do not wish to see
the outcome, Lord?
No. No, I do not.
My dear,
will you ask the nurses
to fetch the children?
I wish to walk with them.
[grunting]
[grunts]
Huh?
[screams]
[man]
The Danes! The Danes are here!
They have breached
the city walls!
Save yourselves!
The fight is finished arseling!
Come on. Run.
Stand to a man!
They are not to pass!
They are not to
approach the palace!
Father they will hack
the likes of us into pieces.
The king! Where is the king?!
The king will have to make
his own arrangements.
And what of me? Odda! Odda!
[Uhtred]
Leofric, this way!
[grunting]
[screaming]
Go, quickly.
[horse whinnies]
Come on!
There will be nothing left
in the stables but horse shit!
Let's go this way.
[women screaming]
[grunts]
[groans]
We hide here,
wait for nightfall.
I want the king and I want him
alive, crawling on his knees!
[screaming]
[chuckles]
[Guthrum]
Find me, Alfred!.
[screaming]
Keep away! Keep away!
Stand back, I warn you.
God will protect me...
God will...
[screams]
[gasps for air]
Only Guthrum can save you.
Guthrum is your God now.
Should I spare you?
Please...
Go in peace...
Go!
Find Alfred...
[man speaks indistinct]
You are Guthrum...
the great warrior.
I am Aethelwold...
...son of King Aethelred
and rightful King of Wessex.
Alfred stole my crown.
This crown.
As king,
I am prepared to negotiate.
End of negotiation.
[sniffs]
You smell like
you shit yourself.
Well, I've not been well.
[yells]
I pledge to you my allegiance!
[groans]
[indistinct chatter]
[groaning]
[screams in pain]
[woman screams indistinct]
No. No. No!
No!
[screaming]
[man]
Yeah, get her!
Lord you are with me,
you will not desert me.
I feel nothing...
except your love.
Is...
[man] Lookout!
[screams in pain]
[grunting]
[grunts]
They are gone,
they are gone. It is over.
[screams]
-They are gone.
-[panting]
We need to be gone ourselves.
Put on a helmet.
We are Danes.
-Again?
-You will not be leaving me.
-No, we will not.
-You are prisoners.
[barking]
[horses whinny]
[screaming]
[laughing]
[Brida]
Uhtred the Saxon.
Brida!
What's this?
You mean to do me harm?
I haven't decided.
Good to see you again, Brida.
Leofric...
How did you manage
to get such a big head
into such a small helmet?
It was necessary.
Why are you doing this?
Where's Ragnar? Is he here?
He is almost ready
to travel north.
To kill Kjartan?
What do you care?
The guards at the gates
will be drunk.
Your way is clear.
Brida...
Tell Ragnar
I'm still his brother.
I'll tell him you were here
and that you left.
Arseling...
Brida has changed...
She was always angry;
now, she is nasty.
[heavy sigh]
Either she has changed
or I have changed.
She once loved you...
Not anymore.
Even I could see that much.
I hate the forest.
Where's your wife?
I know you are married
to the Lady Mildrith.
She will have sought refuge...
with the church.
She used to come to the Nunnery.
I would pray with her.
I watched her as she changed.
Why does a woman become a nun?
Because of her love for God...
God will never abandon her.
You were being humped
against your will.
Where was God?
He sent you.
Is the king likely
to have been killed?
The king is not our concern.
If the king is dead
then Wessex is dead.
Where are you going?
I need darkness...
She needs darkness for what?
[sighs]
To see.
[soft chuckle]
[nun]
Leofric, where are we?
[Leofric] We are at the
marshlands of the Severn.
The swamplands...
I have never seen
lands like this before.
Hurry, they have seen us,
the boat's won't wait.
Priests.
-Come quickly, we need to leave.
-Hurry...
In fear.
[horses whinny]
[nun] God preserve us.
Time to fight, arseling!
Come on!
[indistinct yelling]
[screams in pain]
Uhtred!
[yelling]
Arseling...
I have your sword.
We will get you!
I hope you're carrying silver,
priest; we have saved your life.
I am saved by ghosts, it seems.
Lord!
Thank God, you are unhurt.
[Alfred]
I was blessed.
-And your family?
-Are safe.
they are in the boat ahead.
Hoping to find sanctuary
in these marshlands.
At the palace Lord,
they came from nowhere.
They did.
They came because
they were allowed to.
Where were your watchers?
Your spies?
-On their knees no doubt.
-You should show respect.
Wessex allows its warriors
to kill each other
and spends too much time
on its knees
and too much money
on its churches.
If Guthrum were Christian
and not Pagan,
there would be no war.
But he's not.
You will do well to remember
that I am king.
-King of what? Look around you.
-He is our king.
Like every kingdom before it,
Wessex has fallen.
He is Alfred, a man,
king of nothing.
[baby coughs, cries]
Lord God,
allow your blessed oils
to penetrate and take away any
and all fever and sickness.
Restore health
and strength to the child
and to his ever
watchful parents. Amen.
-Amen.
[shushing]
Lord, I have prepared a tonic.
For the pain.
For the pain you suffer here.
You pass blood?
From your arse?
It is nothing more than what grows
from the earth Lord, drink it.
-[groans softly]
-It is good?
Oh, not at all.
Thank you.
There will be more, tomorrow.
He will become lost,
I guarantee it.
Were you worried
that I would lose my way?
One path looks like another.
-You have explored?
-A little.
What do you notice,
about this place?
It's wet.
There are no horizons.
No sense of something beyond.
My priests have visited here
once or twice, to preach.
The people are oblivious to God.
You look tired.
Sleep has been a rarity, yes.
My wife would like us
to take a ship to Frankia.
To become another king in exile?
So you admit I am still a king?
We dare not travel,
my son would never survive it.
You should send out word
that you are alive;
asking men to join you,
to follow you.
And then what? Fight?
-Is that what you would do?
-It's what a king would do.
I have given it thought,
of course I have,
and this much I know:
if I am to fight, it would have
to be a single battle, and soon.
Before yet more Danes arrive,
before Wessex crumbles,
skirmish by skirmish,
raid by raid, piece by piece.
Therefore,
the first task would be
to somehow convince the Danes
to hold one great
and deciding moment.
-A single defining battle.
-Yes.
Who would I send?
Out into the country,
with the news I am here?
It would have
to be your priests,
all of them,
each in a separate direction.
Their prayers are needed here.
Your son grows weaker
despite their prayers.
For that I am sorry.
Every breath
is an effort for him.
[crying]
I don't know whether to
make him warm or keep him cool.
Well, we will... We will remain
here until he is well.
[baby cries loudly]
[Uhtred]
Will the child die?
Can you save him?
There is a way...
...though it is not a good way.
If it is the only way,
then you must.
You are feeling
a little better, Lord?
I am.
Iseult is a healer.
She could help your son.
Thank you.
If you help,
then you better succeed.
If the child dies,
you will be blamed.
-We cannot do nothing.
-That is not what I am saying.
Iseult is a Pagan
and a woman.
She will be blamed,
regardless of her meaning well.
If it's true that Alfred
is in the swamp-land;
how long do we wait for him
to come out?
If he is hiding in the swamp-land
we would be fools to go searching.
Have you ever
seen anything like this?
Monasteries
keep words like this.
No, no, not like this.
What does it all mean?
What does all this speak of?
I cannot say I care.
Whatever Alfred found out about
his enemies, he'd write.
Yeah. It's magic.
Yeah, it is.
[both laughing]
-You're laughing!
-It's a weak kind of magic.
No, you are wrong. This is...
It is words without sound.
It is voices without people.
I am going to learn how
to use this magic.
If we took Alfred,
he could teach you.
Only a fool would march an army
into a swamp-land.
Are you that fool?
Are you that fool, Ragnar?
No, I'm not.
Then we wait...
[birds chirping]
We need to be closer.
[arrow hisses]
[animal yells]
Uhtred... the water is rising.
Lord, you had one task.
Oh, I am sorry.
[Iseult clears throat]
I've never cooked before,
and never again I fear.
Are they burned?
They are done well, Lord,
a challenge
for your teeth and stomach.
[soft chuckle]
I have seen a fleet
on the Severn.
They carry Skorpa's colors.
-How many ships?
-Twenty, or more.
That's over one thousand men,
Guthrum will have the same.
-More.
-God save us.
We can save ourselves.
We must believe it.
[baby coughing]
[shushing]
Will the Lady
be joining us, Lord.
Um, no. She will not.
She is angry with me still;
for sending away the priests.
[Uhtred] Sending out the priests
was the right thing, Lord.
Let us pray you are correct.
If you will excuse me.
If the child dies, it will take
the fight from Alfred's bones.
And we will never
save ourselves.
Aelswith.
You must end this silence.
The priests will fetch men.
Without men,
safe passage to the south
and to Frankia
would be impossible.
At best our children
would be taken as slaves.
You are eating meat. Why?
These last few days
the pains have abated.
Meat does not agree.
I could not cope
with further sickness.
In the mind of Brother Asser,
she is a witch, and yet
you gladly drink her potions.
-It is a tonic.
-I can read you.
You wish to put our child
in the hands of the devil!
Our prayers
are not being answered.
Is it any wonder we find ourselves
living in a muddy puddle?!
[baby coughing]
Father, please...
Come, we'll sit by the fire.
I bring word.
From the king.
He lives?
Wessex lives
and breathes, Wulfhere.
Thank God.
Oh, my goodness she has
the nerve to approach.
She has helped me.
Thank you.
[baby coughing and crying]
I, for one, do not wish
to hear your voice.
Do not speak a word.
Is there something you wish
to say, Iseult?
If you wish, Lord,
I will try and help your child.
-We do not wish.
-Tonight is a good night.
We do not wish!
Tomorrow,
it will be too late.
What kind of talk is that?
What kind of talk is "too late!"
Are you saying
that my child will die!
[Alfred]
Aelswith. Aelswith please.
Get her away from me.
Get her away from me!
-Get her out of my sight!
-Please. Stop.
-Lord, she is offering help.
My priests told me that you are
a witch, and they are correct!
She is no witch!
Aelswith please no more.
No more. No more.
You are upsetting yourself,
and you are upsetting
the children, no more!
[baby crying]
No, no, no...
Please, no, no...
Go, go, please.
Iseult, you must prepare.
[shushing]
Lord, it can only be tonight.
She'll be ready.
-[baby crying]
-[Alfred shushing]
The child will pass from
one chamber... to the other.
From near death to life.
What is it?
If this child is to live,
then another,
somewhere, must die.
I will be taking a life,
a stranger, an innocent.
Iseult...
...this must be done.
Lady Aelswith?
Leave me.
I cannot.
Lady, you need comfort.
When a child suffers...
...the mother suffers.
I know this.
I know the pain you feel...
it's almost unbearable.
Even for a queen.
I'll stay only for as
long as you need me.
For a moment or a year.
He's dying...
[sobs]
She is a Pagan.
And yet she has helped the king.
I am to trust a stranger
with my child.
There is good in Iseult.
[baby coos]
[Alfred]
I don't know what is worse,
when he is cries
or when he is still...
When he is still, I feel
the need to prod him awake.
It is retribution.
God is punishing me.
-For what?
-For Aethelwold, for taking his crown.
Aethelwold is a fool;
he could never be king.
Your God is testing you.
Lord, give Edward to Iseult.
If God will not cure Edward,
what makes you think he would
allow a Pagan to succeed?
Who is to say that God
is not working through us all?
Did he not make the Pagans, too?
Beocca would tell me that
God's ways
are known only to himself.
You have been brought
to the marshes for a reason.
You have this one chance
to save your son,
and you will have one chance
to save your kingdom.
The two are bound together.
Edward is your heir.
If he lives,
I would say it's a sign:
Wessex will live.
[sighs]
There is barely a heartbeat.
Let me give the child to Iseult.
May God have mercy
on each of us.
Where is he taken him?
Am I allowed to know?
To Iseult.
God is watching.
[Beocca's voice echos]
Lord?
Good morning, Lord.
We received your message
and came as quickly as we could.
Father Beocca? Is that you?
Yes, Lord.
-You are here?
-I am Lord.
And you have brought men;
Wulfhere!
Lord.
Well... how warming
it is to see you all.
It is good
to see you again, Lord.
And many more are nearby.
Guards, men,
even the Brother Asser is here.
We have all been saying prayers
for your health and safety.
-Praying, yes.
-[Beocca] And for Edward, of course.
Every priest in the land
has been instructed
to hold service
for his recovery.
For Edward; I am blessed.
How is the boy, Lord?
Edward?!
Lord?
What is it, Lord?
[panting]
Oh, please God,
please God, no.
Oh, say he has not been
taken from me.
No, Lord,
this is not his grave.
[baby coos]
He is well, Lord.
What?
And he is healed.
Healed?
Lord, what is this?
It is good news father. Rejoice.
He is well.
[chuckles]
He is well. It is true.
He's...
He is well. He is cool.
He is well, Beocca.
I can... I can feel his heart,
beating strongly.
God has not forsaken you, Lord.
Fetch Aelswith,
fetch his mother!
The prayers of the whole
of Wessex have been answered!
-Indeed.
-Every mass, Lord!
every mass said by 100 priests
or more has been heard!
Look at him.
Look at him, he is well!
God is good! Praise Him!
Yes, praise Him, Father Beocca.
You did well...
Why the tears?
They are for the stranger's child.
[crying]
You are wet, arseling.
I am... Wet, tired,
but I have a plan.
Lord, the ships are guarded
by no more than 60 men.
The rest of the army will be
inland looking for food.
We kill the men,
we burn the ships.
You really believe Skorpa
would then go to Guthrum?
I do.
One army, one battle.
It's the only way, Lord.
It begins here,
in these waters.
You were brought here
for this reason, Lord.
[indistinct chatter]
They need to give chase and they
need to believe they can reach us.
We stand our ground until
the very last moment.
Then we stay on the safe path
and let the land half
kill them before we attack.
And if they do reach us?
Ready?
Remember, don't kill them,
just make them mad.
[arrow hisses]
[arrow sticks]
Another.
[men grumble]
Are you wishing to die?!
Another.
Who are you, you piece of
weasel shit?
You want me to spill your guts?
Here I am, I am waiting.
We will send each of you
to Corpse Hall.
Hit the big bastard!
Come and fight!
Are you afraid?
[all grumble]
[yelling]
We stand our ground.
Run! Run, run, run, run!
[screaming in pain]
[man] Now!
[all groaning in pain]
Now for the ships!
A new horizon, Lord.
A beacon of hope.
God has tested you, Lord,
He has put you into the fire,
as a smith would his steel.
And, like the steel,
you have emerged stronger.
Praise Him.
Praise Him, Lord.
You are right Beocca,
God works in the
strangest of ways,
known only to Himself.